Sarah Moore Field Collection MS261
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Sarah Moore Field Collection
circa 1904 -- 1908
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
William Morris Hunt Memorial Library
MS261
27.05 Linear Feet 1 record carton; 6 oversize rolled item storage boxes; 3 oversize boxes; 1 portfolio; 1 half letter-size document box; and 14 paintings.
This collection includes paintings, drawings, art supplies, sketchbooks, and educational records pertaining to the artistic education of Sarah Moore Field, who attended the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston from January 1904 to January 1908.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, 2019, accession MS-2020-005.
Biographical / Historical
Sarah Moore Field was born on January 31, 1885 to Herbert Webster Field and Julia McDuffie Field in North Andover, Massachusetts. Herbert Field was a banker, and Julia Field may have been an art teacher before her marriage. Sarah Moore Field attended the local grammar school in North Andover and the Abbot Academy, which later became a part of the Phillips Academy. While a student at Abbot Academy, Field studied under Angelica Patterson, who taught composition and design and brought her students to Boston museums. She also had private painting lessons from Mrs. G. Copp of Lawrence, Massachusetts. Field paid for a full term at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts in 1903. After completing her studies at Abbot Academy in 1904, she entered the School of the Museum of Fine Arts.
Field studied at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts from January 1904 through January 1908, though perhaps not continuously. She elected the Department of Drawing and Painting curriculum over the design course of study. While a student, she took courses in drawing from plaster casts, live models, introductory painting, portraiture and advanced painting, anatomy, still life, and perspective. In her first year, she took antique drawing and anatomy with Philip Leslie Hale. The following year, Field took a perspective class with Anson K. Cross. In January 1906, she enrolled in Hale's life drawing class. In her third year, Field began painting and studied with Frank Benson. She copied paintings by Degas, Chardin, and others whose work was held at the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston. In 1907, Field took Edmund Tarbell's portrait class.
In January 1908, Field withdrew from school due to illness. Although she had left only minor requirements unfulfilled, she never finished her degree. She corresponded with Alice Brooks at the School in November 1912 regarding finishing the work required to receive her diploma—an examination in anatomy and a series of perspective drawings—but she did not complete the requirements.
In spite of her illness, Field pursued education and training in several other fields of study after leaving the School of the Museum of Fine Arts. She trained at the Posse Normal School for Gymnastics in Boston as a physical therapist. In 1914, she attended Miss Farmer's School of Cookery and in 1920 earned a certificate in the Special Course in Gasoline Motor Car Operative Principles from the YMCA Automotive School. Field was a philanthropist and her contributions to the American Red Cross during both World Wars were recognized. She managed her real estate, stock investments, home, and gardens until she was in her 90s. She also managed the Field family's papers and artifacts and hoped that the Field home would one day be opened to the public.
Field died on May 6, 1988 in North Andover, Massachusetts. After her death, the family papers and artifacts were sold to benefit the Trinitarian Congregational Church in North Andover, Massachusetts or donated to regional historical societies, museums, and archives.
Custodial History
Prior to her death, Sarah Moore Field managed and preserved a collection of papers and belongings related to the Field family, including material from her time as a student at the School of the Museum of Fine Arts. After her death, the executors of her will, in collaboration with the Trinitarian Congregational Church, donated select objects from the collection to regional museums and historical societies. A portion of the collection was sold to benefit the Trinitarian Congregational Church in North Andover, Massachusetts.
Material related to Sarah Moore Field's studies at the Museum School were donated by the executors of the Sarah Moore Field estate to the Archives of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston and the School of the Museum of Fine Arts in 1998. The original accession numbers from the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston Libraries and Archives were 2016-17, March 10, 2016; 2016-22, March 14, 2016; and 2019-16, August 14, 2019. The School of the Museum of Fine Arts became a part of Tufts University's School of Arts and Sciences in 2016, and in 2019, the collection was transferred to Digital Collections and Archives at Tufts University.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes paintings, drawings, art supplies, sketchbooks, and educational records pertaining to the artistic education of Sarah Moore Field, who attended the School of the Museum of Fine Arts from January 1904 to January 1908. The collection includes framed and unframed paintings of still lifes and portraits on canvas, charcoal drawings on paper, perspective and anatomy studies, and textbooks. Many items are copies of works on display at the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston. The art supplies includes paint, brushes, canvases, pens, pencils, sandpaper, sponges, ink, palettes, rulers and straight edges, and stencils. There are also a small number of photographs, presumably used as studies for other work, reports from the School of the Museum of Fine Arts, clippings and correspondence, and receipts.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in one series in the order in which it was received.
Other Finding Aids
An item-level inventory was received with transfer and is available upon request.
Art--Study and teaching; William Morris Hunt Memorial Library; School of the Museum of Fine Arts
- Sarah Moore Field Collection, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000001
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged in received order.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains artwork and class notes created by School of Museum of Fine Arts student Sarah Moore Field, as well as art supplies. Artwork includes oil paintings of animals, landscapes, and still lifes; charcoal figure drawings; perspective and anatomy studies; and study drawings in charcoal, watercolor, and pencil. This series also contains textbooks, notebooks, exhibit catalogues, and a small quantity of clippings and correspondence.
  - Perspective studies, portraits, and art supplies, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000002 (Box 2)
  - Works on paper and painting of dog on tray, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000003 (Box 4)
  - Three charcoal drawings of nude figures, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000004 (Box 9)
    Two drawings of men and one drawing of a woman holding and looking into a mirror.
  - Four charcoal drawings of nude figures, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000005 (Box 10)
    Drawings of nude woman holding pitcher, nude woman seated on chair covered with cloth, nude figuring lying on stomach, nude man standing.
  - Four charcoal drawings of nude figures, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000006 (Box 11)
    Three drawings of nude figures and one drawing of a clothed figure.
  - Four charcoal drawings of nude figures, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000007 (Box 12)
    Drawings of nude woman standing, nude woman leaning on column, nude man holding pole, nude man standing.
  - Six charcoal drawings and studies of nude figures, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000008 (Box 13)
    Five sketches and studies of nude figures and one drawing of cast of Discus Thrower.
  - Four charcoal drawings of nude figures, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000009 (Box 14)
    Two unfinished drawings of nude figures, one drawing of nude figure, and one drawing of a Michaelangelo sculpture.
  - Art supplies, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000010 (Box 15)
  - Drawings and photographs, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000011 (Box 16)
  - Sketch books, notebooks, and oil paintings, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000012 (Box 17)
  - Clippings and correspondence, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000013 (Box 18)
  - Landscape painting on stretched canvas, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000014 (Object 1)
  - Unfinished pencil sketch of horse with perspective lines on stretched canvas, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000015 (Object 3)
  - Oil painting of pansies in wooden frame, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000016 (Object 5)
  - Oil painting of still life of vase, bowl, and candlestick on stretched canvas, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000017 (Object 6)
  - Oil painting of still life of roses in mug on stretched canvas, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000018 (Object 7)
  - Landscape painting on stretched canvas, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000019 (Object 8)
  - Unfinished portrait of man in profile, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000020 (Object 19)
  - Unfinished portrait of woman in three-quarter profile, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000021 (Object 20)
  - Unfinished portrait of woman, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000022 (Object 21)
  - Oil painting of horses and jockeys, copy of Degas, in wide gold frame with light attached, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000023 (Object 22)
  - Oil painting of still life with white pitcher, mortar and pestle, and copper kettle, in wide wood frame, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000024 (Object 23)
  - Oil painting of still life of decanter, oranges, and blue and white plate in double frame, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000025 (Object 24)
  - Portrait of "The Cavalier," a bearded man in broad-brimmed hat, with pipe, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000026 (Object 25)
  - Oil painting of landscape in winter on wood panel, circa 1904 -- 1908; MS261.000027 (Object 26)